I think
it's okay great so uh let's start so
this is the the
third segment of my uh coverage of
classical Robotics and this is the
problem of motion
planning and uh and this is again a
problem which was like the burning topic
of the 1980s and '90s but my belief is
essentially by the ' 90s it was Sol okay
and uh so what's the the problem the
problem is we have a robot in some start
configuration and we want it to go to
some goal configuration while avoiding
obstacles so there are many settings of
this problem depending on the robot and
what space and what obstacles and so on
so there's obviously a simple-minded
version which is you have a mobile robot
roaming around on this floor and it
doesn't collide with chairs and tables
and so or you can talk about the is for
your uh uh Frank arm and it has to move
and get to a desired configuration in
that case it's going to be in some six
degree of Freedom space and it has to
avoid colliding with obstacles and not
only should the the hand of the robot
not Collide but while it's moving the
elbow shouldn't bang and destroy your
precious
mingas okay so uh how do we do this so
uh I
can start with this baby example so this
baby example is about uh two link robot
so it has it's on the left so you have
Theta 1 and Theta 2 uh so those are the
two degrees of freedom and then uh we
have a robot arm which is kind of here
right it's the this is the base of the
robot arm it has to go it has to be go
from here to there so there's the start
configuration so what you need to do is
and these are obstacles so this A and B
and C are
obstacles so what this arm needs to do
is to kind of retract and then move and
then end up in that configuration
right so uh uh so so so this is the
problem so basically you have to avoid
not just colliding Collision of the end
affector but also with any part of the
robot no part of the robot should
collide with an obstacle so how do we do
this okay and as I said this was all
worked out in the 1980s and '90s
and uh so one concept which is important
is the concept of configuration
space or here it's abbreviated as
c-space
configuration I mean this term comes
from physics configuration is whatever
suppose you have a system of particles
in a box then you describe how do you
describe the configuration it's really
like the position of every particle and
its momentum something like that
sometimes we use the term stra space for
a similar concept so the configuration
space for the robot is uh in the joint
angle space so Theta 1 Theta 2 so that's
what you see on the right so this
diagram is Theta 1 Theta to okay now uh
but you have these
obstacles a b c so these obstacles are
some areas in R2 that we do not want to
go to so what you can do is you can
translate
them because you know the kinematics of
the robot you can translate them into
where they would be in configuration
space so that is shown here by this a is
the uh conversion from sort of ukian
space to Joint angle space of this
obstacle a where you have B which is the
conversion of obstacle B into
configuration space similarly for this
and why these look funny is because with
this joint angles the relationship
between that and R2 involves all these
trigonometric functions of ss and
cosiness and so on so that's why the
shapes are going to look funny
so is this clear configuration space
which is sometimes abbreviated as
c-space in c-space which is like the
joint angle space we can take all the
obstacles and and and put them
there so far so good so this was uh
worked out by Lozano
Perez okay but now uh this is correct if
the robot is a point robot but the robot
is not a point robot the robot may have
some
uh like a mobile robot moving around in
space might have be a might have a
diameter of half a meter or something
and then your ca arm or Frank arm also
has some finite thickness so how do we
deal with that so here is a one way of
solving this problem so what you have
here is there is this XY space and then
there is this
obstacle obstacle shown by this triangle
which is a shaded in Gray and my my
robot is a dis right so this is my robot
disc so what do I do with my robot disc
either I have to take do some
complicated stuff with my robot dis or
what I do is I just grow all the
obstacles right so I grow the obstacle
by this by corresponding to the radius
of this uh this uh mobile robot okay so
that is what is shown here okay so you
take the real obstacles you grow them
appropriate uh to the size of the robot
and then when we solve the path planning
problem for avoiding obstacles we just
deal with the a point so a point has to
move in space we don't have to consider
the fact that the robot has some
diameter so you have just modified the
c-space so we did two conversions so the
first conversion is going from ukian
space to uh to configuration space with
joint angles the second was that you
grow the obstacles by an amount
corresponding to the physical uh
dimensions of the robot like its width
and so on so far so
good okay and now you suddenly can get
into uh problems which uh I mean I mean
correct the problems are real not big so
suppose you had these two obstacles
right so it looks like oh there's a path
between them
but if your robot is a fat robot it has
a certain radius and with that radius
robot it cannot go through that Gap and
that is revealed by the fact that once
you have you have expanded all the
obstacles you have grown the obstacles
corresponding to the size of the robot
then the these uh these configur these
obstacles actually intersect that means
that there's no Gap there so what we do
is we we do this kind of transformation
in the beginning and then uh then we
have a setting of the problem where
there is some space And Then There are
all these
obstacles okay does that make sense now
uh note that here my background as a
computer vision person has to come in so
this is the standard framing of the
problem in robotics and I can assure you
if you read the literature from the
1980s 990s this is just carried through
with without with near a doubt but as a
computer version person the first thing
I will have to say is how do you know
where the obstacles are there's a
perception system which has to reveal
where they are and the perception system
is always going to be incomplete and
error
proof right so therefore assuming that
all the obstacles are known completely
and exactly this is
simplifying modeling assumption but it
leaves a lot to be
desired and I think you should also note
that do we really need to know all the
obstacles I mean there might be I mean
ultimately you're going to do a task
like like your robot has to go and pick
up the coffee mug and it may not need to
know all the configuration space
obstacles everywhere on this flow it
just needs to not hit anything while
getting to that much so so so we need to
take this into account and the solutions
we have today will try to take this into
account so when we when we unpack the
box of learning of perception which was
not common in the in the 80s and ' 90s
you there was this abstraction of
perfect perception and then you solve
the robot motion planning problem as
essentially a computational geometry
problem and you could solve it very
cleanly but that came at a cost the cost
was that Perfection was assumed to be
perfect and complete which is not a
Justified assumption and the solutions
we'll try to come up with today we'll
have to go beyond those classical
Solutions but you can only go beyond the
classical Solutions after being aware of
the classical Solutions so that is why
I'm giving this
lecture okay so we got this we got this
uh okay and uh so what is the key
finding so the key finding is that we
can take this configuration
space and uh and we are really concerned
with the free space part so C free is
the free part of configuration space and
this could be in some higher dimensional
setting depending on the dimensionality
of your robot and so on so in this space
you it turns out that it can uh that you
can find a a one Di
dimensional road map with okay and and
then the following is true that uh so
you you let's say you find this road map
R which is this onedimensional
entity and now we can solve the problem
of going from any start state to any
gold state by the following the start
space will may not be at on this road
map which is okay what you do is from
the starts
State you go you get to the road map
it's like you want to drive on the
highway system first you get to the
highway system okay then you travel on
the road map and then you take an exit
and you get to your goal
State okay so that's the framing of the
problem and this framing is uh complete
framing in the sense that this if there
is a solution which exists it can be
found in this way and the person who
worked on uh this in detail was John
cany who is one of our colleagues here
at Berkeley so John canny's PhD thesis
was essentially on how to calculate
these road maps
analytically okay and then
uh so uh and so there are these
properties here which is reachability
which is essentially saying intuitively
that you can uh from from the from free
configurations space from some point in
the free part of configuration space you
can get to the road map and then you can
exit similarly and then uh if the
configuration the free part of
configuration space is connected then
there is one connected component of R
because if if the if this free space is
not connected then there's nothing you
can do you cannot go from the start
state to the gold state if they are in
disconnected parts of the space so that
cannot be problem cannot be solved
is that is that clear so so the idea is
that you're projecting down this more
complicated problem to the problem of
finding this this onedimensional road
map and then you solve the problem there
but this is it turns out to be very hard
because essentially you can see from the
nature of these constraints and the that
you're going to get all this uh there is
not a linear problem I mean you you can
see it from the pictures
so it involves what has called
semialgebraic sets and just don't ask me
to explain what the that stuff is okay
and uh so so so John cany thesis
provided a
theoretically complete solution but in
practice this was very hard to implement
and carry out because of uh the fact
that essentially it required all these
tools of algebraic
geometry and so there was an alternative
Techni technology which was developed uh
starting from uh work at Stanford and
then uh uh I mean essentially kavaki and
latom is the key one of the key early
papers and in this what was done was
that instead of trying to solve
analytically for this road map uh there
was a probabilistic sampling type
approach which was done and uh uh I have
this figure here which shows what the
probabilist take road map looks like
okay or one of them I mean there can be
many so basically so there are some
obstacles here and you you still have
this one dimensional structure here it's
it's a graph but it's a one dimensional
structure and it is a set of points in
free space connected by edges and the
idea is that two points are connected by
an edge if there is an easy way to get
from one to the other for example by a
straight line path so in fact one way to
think about it is that like just just
think of this as okay I am at station a
and there's the station C and I can see
as direct path from a to c so I can do I
don't need to do any fancy planning I
just go in a straight line I can get to
see so then I have a edge in the graph
connecting a to c so basically you have
a whole bunch of points okay which are
sampled in this space right and then you
have connectivity based on uh a a simple
local planner like for example just go
in a straight line from A to B uh that
if if that can be done you connected by
an edge now in this
graph how uh how do we solve the problem
we solve the problem now of just graph
verion right so this is your standard
computer science problem you're given a
graph it has some nodes it has some
edges if there you are at some node node
C and some there's some node F uh if can
you find a path between C to F and in
fact you can uh it's a weighted graph
right so you can have edges which
correspond to the length or how much
distance uh you have to travel or how
much time you would have to travel and
then what you do is you can add up those
cost and that's the total cost of going
from some node a to some node
B does that make sense so uh so it's
actually from having to do
very complicated uh algebraic geometry
in computer algebra it was it
was
yeah so so this is this was a transition
which occurred essentially from the 80s
to the 90s okay uh so how do we do this
uh so now uh this problem uh how do we
solve this problem so I've got the
algorithm here okay it is super super
easy okay so first this is the pseudo
code for this PRM so so why PRM RM is
road map so that's John canny's concept
PRM is probabilistic road map so this is
the the work from kavaki and Lon and uh
what's that algorithm this is it this is
all that uh uh you know uh that I need
to explain so you have a whole bunch of
samples which are like these points in
the space okay and now what you do is
you try to find so so initially imagine
that there are no edges okay in fact we
can build up the algorithm this is an
algorithm you can think up in five
minutes right you just sample some
points in the space so now you have all
those little circles yeah but the key
have a a tight
that's the key want you do that low
complexity yeah and that can be done so
that's proving properties but the
algorithm is easy right proving
properties can be hard okay so now what
you do is you are at a point and what
you do is you just find the nearest
three points I think this is the okay so
so I've got like 100 points right
sampled randomly I pick a point and then
I try to find the nearest three point
in ukian distances that's easy right
nearest neighbor algorithm will do that
for you you find the three nearest
neighbor then you ask for each of these
three nearest neighbors can I get there
in a straight line that's also
straightforward you you draw the line
connecting the point A and B and see if
that line intersects an obstacle so that
requires a little bit of work right but
it's just a computation of does this
line intersect an obstacle which can be
done okay and now if it if it you can
achieve that then you draw an edge
between them so now of those three
neighbors maybe two of them you can get
to by a straight line path for the third
one the straight line path gets blocked
by some obstacle so you don't connect an
edge repeat so now at for every every
node you have a sense of what are the
what are nearby points to which you can
go by a straight line path without
hitting obstacles and now you have
constructed the graph so now if I have
to solve a now I do this work in advance
so this is my construction of the PRM
and now suppose I put you somewhere so
if I'm here what should I do and I need
to go to some point which is over there
what I do is from this point I need to
get on the highway system right so you
try to find the nearest edges the the
nearest nodes and see if there's a
straight line Edge to one of them okay
that means I can take the freeway from
University Avenue exit Okay then
similarly for my on the other side from
my gold node I again figure out if there
is some node to which I can get by a
straight line path so now I've got two
nodes on this
graph okay basically this PRM is like
you have freeway system
you have a way to get to the freeway
system and you have a way out of the
freeway system and in between you
solve graph minimum path problem dyra
AAR I mean there there's a you know this
is the stuff we teach the kids right
okay so everybody knows this is that uh
yeah
question I mean it's it's it's the only
thing you can do so it's always so it's
it's uh it can be done but it is it will
be the complexity will go up so so so
now there was an industry after this
which is uh this is the PRM version
which is what you do where initially
where you if you have to solve many
versions of the problem you create this
PRM once and pay the cost for it and
after that you can do any query quickly
now suppose you have to solve just one
version of setting of the problem then
it seems like too much work right uh so
you should do more less work and then
there are these algorithms called rrt
and rrt star and rapidly exploring
something something so again books have
been written on that stuff but
conceptually what you what I've told you
is all you that you know and now uh let
me again put in the The Vision person's
critique of this this whole setup so
what's the vision person's critique of
this setup okay first let me get to the
final picture Okay so the algorithm is I
I told you it is you can't it's as
simple as this so what's the vision
person's critique of this setup it
builds on what huh yeah you do not know
all the obstacles in advance right and
this thing will keep changing and do you
I do I really need to know about all the
obstacles everywhere on this floor in
order to solve this problem so this is
this is an example
of uh I think I think now I'm
editorializing I mean in classical
robotics these are some of the the the
the the issues which I find
unsatisfactory so one is this this sharp
distinction between perception and
action so you say you assume that there
exists a perfect perception system which
creates this complete map of the world
okay and so the map of the obstacles and
so and and you say okay you perception
system you guys get to it you do this
job and I'll talk to you only after that
and then the sponsor of a vision person
is no I'm not going to do it okay but
the vision the robotics people say I
need to write papers I'm going to assume
that this will be delivered to me and
now I will proceed beyond that so this
is a fundamental divide which today's
work goes beyond okay and then we get
into the there's a learning aspect which
is separate so there's a perception
aspect and a learning aspect which in
modern robotics we sort of have to take
both of those seriously but in classical
robotics you uh you sort of bypassed
that by assuming that perception was
perfect so now it was just a
computational geometry problem it was a
beautiful elegant setting so in in that
era I mean I mean this was work being
done by my colleagues here I would look
at the robotics talk and I would look at
the talk and vision and inv Vision
nothing worked and the robotics people
in this setting they could solve
everything
right and and and so it's interesting
that now Vision Works yeah but uh uh
that so this is uh uh okay so so I think
this is my summary slide usually we
assume the geometry is fully known this
is a
critique uh we can do this uh uh so uh
so we we will re re-approach this topic
a bit later when we try to solve the
problem
for uh navigation and in navigation it's
turned out that really the problem is
not as hard as it seems and because what
you need are very good heuristics when
you're so when I'm trying to solve the
problem of navigating from here to the
door it's actually not a hard problem
and it's mostly a vision problem because
uh that we do not have these very very
complicated spaces so so this is the the
these configuration space algorithms are
were like you're were in the setting of
classical theoretical computer science
which is that you're dealing with the
worst case right whereas we don't have
to deal with the worst case we in fact
design environment such that it's not
difficult to navigate I mean if you had
to solve a uh complicated o of n6
problem every time you want to go from
here to the door you would say this
architect was terrible right or this
house is very cluttered we don't live in
that kind of world so uh so from here
it's easy right where is free space I
mean I just go there and then I go there
and you just can solve the problem
locally and uh and that sometimes
doesn't work because you can get into
dead ends so but if you have some
mechanism for backtracking and so forth
you can work this out and we'll do
examples of that when we study
navigation so it doesn't really need to
make the assumption that the world is
fully known a prior we can uh we can do
the perception as we go along the
perception is incomplete it is noisy and
yet we can uh we can plan
pass
okay uh uh so let me let me uh do five
minutes on this uh this other classical
problem which is going from paths to
trajectories so this is mostly about
understanding what uh the terminology so
what's the difference between a path and
a
trajectory okay so uh a path okay okay
I'll do it by writing okay so let me
write okay so what is a path the path is
the
sequence uh
uh I mean of of positions on this curve
trajectory is the sequence of positions
as a function of
time so when we
write right you can have information
which is just the sequence XY XY pairs
on my signature or I could have the
functions X of T comma y of T and
obviously the second carries more
information because from from that you
can derive the the path so in fact way
back like 20 30 years ago when people
were developing uh signature recognition
systems there were two versions of the
problem so there's the OCR version where
you just have the signature as an image
and you need to recognize it or there is
a version where you do it with a stylus
on some tablet or something like that
and then you have access to the
trajectory
information and no surprise that version
the problem is easier and for which you
have better Solutions so this is it
that's the difference between path and
trajectory so trajectory
requires uh trajectory is a
specification of the configuration as a
function of time right easy State X as a
function of time path is that you just
have this as a function of arc length
and then uh how do you go between the
two you can Define What's called the
time scaling so the time scaling will
essentially map from this uh the notion
of time to coordinates on that curve or
the standard way to parameterize that
curve is what's called Arc Length so you
measure distance along the curve as you
go from uh one end point to the other
and now as you are moving along that
curve you associate also that also with
a with a time stamp and that's called
time scaling so now uh so now uh let me
give a very intuitive example suppose I
want to reach and pick up an object so
the trajectory is about uh the uh okay
what's the path the path is the position
in ukian space of my uh hand and arm and
so on the trajectory refers to this as a
function of time and what do you expect
the trajectory to have so initially I'm
at stationary then I'm going to
accelerate so I'm moving fast and then
I'm going to slow down by the time I
actually uh come to touch the object
right that's what you expect because the
end State you don't when you are going
to pick up a cup you don't want to
destroy the Cup by banging at it at some
high speed right and you're going to
start out at rest so you're going to
start at rest end at rest so the
velocity should be zero at the end
points in between you accelerate but you
don't want to accelerate super fast in
some you want to accelerate in a smooth
way so this game is what's the the the
game about sort of uh time scaling and
and so forth and again it's a Well
worked out problem there's nothing
complicated here uh small observation
which is uh when we say straight line
straight line in what space they could
be straight line in joint angle space or
they could be straight line in task
space so task space sometimes people use
the term operational space this refers
to sort of the ukian space in which the
object actually is and a straight line
in joint angle space may not be a
straight line in in task space and uh
okay uh and and this is like a
reasonable thing to do you you start at
velocity zero you accelerate smoothly
you keep moving and then you slow down
and similar observations have been made
by human so we can monitor human hands
as as they are reaching to pick up an
object and and you can uh you can see
this behavior and kids when they start
they are not so smooth but as
kids develop have with practice picking
up objects they develop these smooth
trajectories any questions on
this
okay so far so good so I think
trajectory is a uh you know the
distinction between the path and a
trajectory so the earlier uh uh segment
of the lecture when I was talking about
robot path planning I was just talking
about the path and then you would
convert the path into a trajectory and
then you can Implement robot though of
course I have to recall that we doing it
the wrong way because we are assuming
that we have this complete knowledge of
the environment which is not quite the
right thing to do okay and now I have 15
minutes to do what was originally meant
to be a 1hour lecture and it's fine I
think I need to just uh so I'm going to
uh do short shift to neuroscience and
just uh convey a few ideas and uh
because we have learned so much about
the basic uh vocabulary of Dynamics and
Robotics I can I think do it more
compactly so I'm going to uh talk about
I think like two or three things and but
I do want want you to read the paper
there are two very good papers that
we'll we put on the reading list so the
first is that uh every field is defined
by its Heroes so the hero for biological
motor control is this the Soviet
scientist called Nikolai
Bernstein this guy was amazing he is
like the the the the deepest thinker in
this field for in the last
century okay so uh so uh he uh and he
was because he was Russian he published
in Russian in the west people did not
know a lot about his work then there was
a time where he fell into trouble with
the with the Russian government so he
was not even known inside Russia he
barely escaped getting you know sent off
to a gulag uh but uh he was
doing experiments in the 1930s and 40s
which people in the west did like 20
years later okay but uh okay so this is
first just phrase of Nikolai Bernstein
and you you should read him uh but he
was uh he appreciated the difficulties
and complexities of Robotics or
essentially the human version of the
problem which is biological motor
control because he was dealing with at
that time there were very simple-minded
theories so for example there was Pavlo
who was a prominent scientist in the
Soviet Union and Pavlo believed in
reflexes which there is a simple-minded
version of reinforcement
learning and uh and uh the idea was you
and and a simple way of thinking about
it would be like a simple feedback
control with just the P term or
something like that and again I'm
grossly simplifying but uh Bernstein
talked about the complexities of the
problem the fact that there would be
variability because it's when the arm is
moving it's never the same condition
because you are carrying different loads
and so on and so forth so again I'm not
going to go into a lecture on Burn
stream but I want to give you uh one
titbit from Burnstein which I liked a
lot which is the so-called degrees of
freedom problem so the degrees of
freedom problem is this which is that uh
when we we we have a multi-jointed
system right humans he's talking about
humans we have many joints and these
many joints have to be controlled and
and uh so therefore there are many
degrees of freedom so if you want to put
it in our jargon of Robotics and
reinforcement learning it's a challenge
of having lots of degrees of freedom
when you're trying to do reinforcement
learning reinforcement learning is
challenging because of the fact that you
are many when you have many degrees of
freedom when you have few degrees of
freedom it's not so bad it's it's the
the because you're going to go
exponential in the number of degrees of
freedom and that's what is problematic
so he had realized this and noticed this
and this is way before any reinforcement
learning or anything like that the other
observation was that we have in us the
ability to execute certain certain
trajectories even though they are
realized in many different ways so I'm
going to give you an example
so okay so I'm going to sign my name
okay
yeah I did that right okay okay now I'm
going to sign my name like
this okay and next I'm imagine that this
is I'm on the beach there is a sand and
with my toe I can sign my
name I can do this right you all can do
this but think about what is going on
here
very very different joints are involved
very very different degrees of freedom
are involved and we can do this so we
have some representation of this task
and trajectory which is realized in
three different ways when I write with a
pen on paper when I write with my arm on
a board and when I uh sign my name with
my big toe on the sun it's totally
different uh joints and so on are being
used but yet the signature would look
pretty pretty much the same okay so
anyway this is an argument for some kind
of a representation so this is one of
his insights then he had theories of how
to solve the degrees of freedom problem
like how do we solve the learning
problem so his thing was that you first
solve it in a low degree of Freedom
setup so his term was freeze the degrees
of freedom so you might have 20 degrees
of freedom but first solve the problem
with four degrees of freedom then solve
it with eight then with 15 and so on and
this idea in computer vision we have a
version of this which is the course to
find hierarchy and it's essentially a
version of that and then there is a now
you have to ask the question is this
actually true in humans when they learn
in the early stages do they use fewer
degrees of freedom so there are and now
you can get into a big debate on this
but anyway I'm I'm I'm giving you some
flavor of the findings of Nikolai
Bernstein which were which were to be
quite interesting and he did both
experimental work by measuring people
perform various kinds of motor actions
and then of course he was a theoretician
so he has a series of books on how he
thinks this is going on work done in the
1930s and 40s right way way back I mean
the kind of sophistication that was so
even so a lot of this when we interpret
today with the tools of control theory
it makes sense and it's we would
describe it much more compactly
mathematically today but he was doing it
at a time when he didn't really have
knowledge of all the the control theory
developments like this at 1960 this guy
did all his work before that so he had
the the right intuition and his I mean I
mean his book are a pleasure to read
because he's also a very educated man
who can talk about many different
things okay so okay next I want to talk
about seven minutes okay that's fine uh
second idea that I want to talk about is
the something which is there a lot in
the in the neural literature and it can
be
explained given the lecture that I've
given you earlier today I can do this
quite compactly so there is something
called the internal model
hypothesis so the internal model
hypothesis is essentially uh uh that we
have a it's it's related to the to what
I said a lecture or two ago about
Kenneth CRA that in our mind we have
some kind of a model of our act ability
to actions and then we use that for
planning because we can kind of run a
forward
simulation so that intuitive idea
has been has emerged in the in the in
the in the biological motor control
Community with the various names so this
is Ito who talked about it for the
cerebellum there's cavato and uh then
Jordan this is Mike Jordan from Berkley
this is part of his PhD thesis with Dave
ramart David ramart is by the way the
inventor of back
propagation okay and and why do we need
uh so so a good thing to think about
here is that these are two kinds of
models we could have the top model is a
straightforward uh it's like the basic
uh feedback model you have some error
you act so like my P controller
example okay and uh it's simple easy I
mean when people talked about reflexes
they were thinking about it in that term
why won't it work the reason why it
won't work work is
because uh the neural network of in our
brain is too damn
slow the vision system is too damn slow
I mean we all the roboticist always
complain about Vision being slow but
this is the same problem that biology
faces so when we have stuff coming from
our retina going up to the brain it's
150 milliseconds it's seven synapses to
it so basically you're going to add this
150 milliseconds of delay and we are
able to perform these very fast uh these
task like catching balls and so on in
with a system which
is has this horrible delay built in okay
so the delay is shorter when you're
talking about like proprioceptive
information and tactile information but
let's say it's 50 milliseconds there
vision is the slowest of the senses so
how how do you deal with that I mean
this is like the challenge that biology
has to confront and the way it deals
with it is essentially shown in this
lower diagram and it's connected to that
computed torque model that I talked
about at the end of the robot control
segment a combination of feed forward
and feedback so you try to rely on uh so
you have a good feedforward model you
know your own body you know the
consequence of your actions you know how
much forces you have to apply to pick up
a light object or a heavy object and so
on so that's the and then there's the
the inverse model is basically what you
use for planning the forward model is
for predicting what will happen and
inverse model is uh what Tor should I
apply right so okay so that gives the
feed forward uh motor command and then
you have some control object and then
you sense so you use a combination of
feed forward and
feedback so we cannot design very simple
systems which would be based just on
feedback because of the simple reason
that uh the visual system is too Dam
slow okay so are the other system with
the vision system is the most extreme so
we have to design in a way such that we
can build that in so you can build that
in with predictive models but those are
basically require this kind of Feit
forward modeling right you need to have
that I mean you need to
yeah no so you can have simpler Vision
systems so it's not it's essentially
about every synapse introduces about 20
milliseconds of DeLay So if you're going
to do more sophisticated processing if
you like your Transformers to have 30
layers right you're going to pay for it
if if you want to Transformer to three
layers it's not it's going to take less
latency but you'll pay for it in the the
expressivity of the of the functions you
can compute have might have a larger
representation that tells you what to do
only come later no no so I I I I mean
obviously we solve the problem because
we do right we exist we use our vision
system I I gave you some flavor of that
in my last lecture which is that how we
use vision is we use Vision to do the
high level planning get some information
like where the location of the objects
are and then the lowlevel control can be
done in a in a feet forward way because
you have a good model of your body so
you're not using Vision continuously to
monitor where your hand is where the
object is that would be too slow and the
so to me this is good news because
basically for years in computer vision
or in robotics we have suffered from the
fact that our networks I mean now
they're better than they used to be but
they are very they are slow but now I do
not worry about this I do not lose sleep
over it because I say if the human brain
and human motor control system can deal
with the delay uh so can we so we should
be able to solve this problem if
anything with technology you know faster
and faster gpus that 150 millisecond
need not be the barrier
right uh whereas we are stuck with the
body we have so we
are uh so anyway that this is the so
read the cavato paper which we'll make
available to you so this is uh it's easy
to understand once you know about feed
forward feed back but in the context of
biology this is a good Exposition and
then I have my last slide which is uh oh
there's a second last slide which is
which gives some example of how the
details of this might be if you're
trying to pick up an object so there
will be a inverse model that you use for
planning you decide uh how much force to
apply uh that inverse model uh uh I mean
you the inference copy is
the what action did you command so you
send that and then you you have some
kind of a feedback at the end which
might involve for example tactile
sensing and so on so we so for example
if the object starts to slip then you
can have a tight control Loop which
increases the the grip Force right so
the the the the biological motor control
system
is designed in this very clever way that
it can cope with the fact that the
vision system is is actually slow and
and yet we get quite robust
performance and I have this absolute
last slide which is I think it's trying
to point out that when we perform
actions so this is something like
picking up an object for example right
so there are going to be these stages so
so this is like pick up and pick up an
object so your arm has to move your hand
has to form the right shape you have to
pick up grasp the object you have to
pick it up right so these are the the
stages of that and you cannot be using
continuous
visual feedback during these these
stages of just moving your hand it's too
slow but there are certain events and
then the point here is that those events
have signatures so there can be a visual
event which is uh you know you you
recognize that you have grasped the
object there's an auditory event you
pick up an object and you put it down
then there's a sound so there's an
auditory event there is a tactile event
when your finger touches an object so
this uh this diagram which is from
neuros another Neuroscience paper shows
that essentially actions have these
different stages and
then at the end of each stage you have
some events and these events have
signatures in the visual domain in the
auditory domain in the tactile
domain again if you think about it it's
common sense but how many of our robotic
systems today really exploit
this so that's what we have to figure
out and I'm done for today